Bam.
>> I'm John Kuryaku and you're watching the
Break It Down Show.
>> John is an awesome dude. My I was having
some trouble with my jump talk and I was
having a hard time getting logged in on
another computer so I had to race across
town and you were great to ride with me.
Thank you for that. Thank you for your
patience.
>> Very happy to do it.
>> Thank you for the work that you're
doing. You know, there's a lot of us out
there trying to figure this out, but I'm
just kind of following your example on
the media thing because you're getting
important messages out and I'm always
having to qualify. This is not a
political statement. You know, this is a
policy statement
>> because we struggle to accept these
realities as as a nation, as a people,
as a political party, whatever it is, we
>> struggle with nuance, I I guess. I don't
know. What do we struggle with, do you
think?
>> We struggle with a lot. Yeah. Nuance is
certainly one of those things that we
struggle with. Yes.
>> Yeah. You know, it's funny. There's to
most Americans,
>> most issues are black and white,
>> right? There's a a right way or wrong
way. Good thing, a bad thing. And that's
just not in my experience, that's not
real life.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I was told all the time when
we were deployed that farmers need this.
So, you know, I'm a I'm a spy. I'm going
to go talk to farmers and I get to know
them, you know, oh, they need this
collective or they need this other
thing.
>> They didn't they didn't ever say maybe
they would get there,
>> but they weren't there that day.
>> Yeah, I agree with that.
>> And that was true across every
initiative that we had that there was
this belief that we knew the problem, we
knew the path, and we knew the outcome.
But Iraqis have all the energy they ever
need to have electricity everywhere. and
they could point to they're like how how
do we not fix this? And then I think
about us if someone lights out the power
or makes it intermittent 18 minutes at a
time, none for three hours, electricity
for five hours, it would drive us crazy.
>> Yeah, we would. You know, I I've got a
very very close friend who goes to Iran
with regularity once, twice a year, and
um
she would always come back and tell me
how great things are there and how
smoothly things are operating there. And
I would think, okay, yeah, sure. And
then she started taking videos of just
everyday normal life,
>> right? and then showing me other
people's videos on YouTube.
And she's right.
You know, there's no US involvement
inside Iran. There hasn't been since 19,
you know, 79. We've got no embassy
there. We have no diplomatic presence.
There's no business presence. There's
there's nothing. And they lack for
nothing. They want for nothing. They
have great relations with Iran, I mean
sorry, with China and with Russia. They
get all the spare parts they need. They
have healthy trade relationships with,
>> you know, all of the the the
regions powers and and larger economies.
And then you look at something like
Iraq, which is right next door,
that has a a very heavy American
presence. And we've wrecked that
country.
>> Yeah. we've we've wrecked it, which was
the plan.
>> But, you know, still,
>> yeah, there's a you know, I built these
rules learning about us, you know, and
one of the things was is uh oh, Iraq is
totally different than Afghanistan. Oh,
that's true, but we're not. We're
[clears throat] the same and we're
running the same playbook.
>> That was one of the first rules.
>> The other ones are uh wherever we go, we
create instability. This is the rule.
And then the second rule is we refuse to
accept rule number one. Yeah.
>> And so we are end up becoming a net
destabilizer. I'm not down on our
foreign policy, but it's just very hard
to get these things right. And when we
are getting them wrong, we refuse to
accept it. We accept responsibility or
anything.
>> You're exactly right.
>> We we don't we don't accept
responsibility. It's true.
>> Yeah. [snorts] Mhm.
>> You
It's It gets frustrating fast. The
illprincipled behavior of the people who
are making these decisions, the choices,
the people they pick and everything. Um
there's no culpability for that. I'm
hard on all of the secretaries of state
like blinking and all this because I saw
him fail his way all the way to the top.
I know that's a saying, but he was awful
and
>> shouldn't have been given control of
American foreign policy because he he
had done the opposite of earning it.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I agree.
>> Is that fixable?
>> I think over the long term it is.
>> Okay.
>> But uh but in the near term, and we're
very much a near-term, you know, kind of
kind of country. Uh I think no I think
one of the things that we underestimate
is um
one of the things we underestimate is
the long-term effects that our foreign
policy has on um on relations
>> because we change presidents every four
years or eight years. We think that that
we can just,
you know, say, "Ah, our bad when we
screw something up. Our bad, no problem.
You know, we'll get it right now." And
and that's just not
that's just not the way it is.
>> Yeah. We're like a drunk uncle. Here's
here's a thousand bucks, kid. Sorry.
>> Exactly.
Exactly.
>> Try going gay. That'll probably help
you. Seriously. Oh my god.
>> Oh my god. that that rotation of
presidents and and uh in and out of
Congress which only exacerbates that our
economy runs our entire nation runs on a
an annual budget. Yeah.
>> That doesn't agree with itself yeartoear
in a lot of ways.
>> That's right. That's right. Which is
another important problem that we have
where for example you know we spend a
trillion dollars a year on on defense
really on offense but we call it defense
>> right? um which year after year after
year after year is more money than the
Pentagon asks for
and then we are apoplelectic that
auditors can't find where the money
went.
>> Oh yeah. Yeah. And also apoplelectic
don't you dare search for that money.
>> That's right. Don't you don't you dare
figure [laughter] out because
>> the the real life ground truth example
of this is you know in 2000 we'll just
make up a year 2006 it's all about
schools building schools this year Pete
and so you run around the battlefield
I'm building schools like hey have you
asked anybody if they need a school
where the schools are what curriculum
they teaching yeah exactly
>> and then the question I was asked by
hire all the most was how many schools
are in that area and I'm like oh man
like you know whatever year it is it's
past the time of that information. We
never we had all this information but no
way to to actually learn it and put it
to work. So I would say back to our
American partner I would say well um one
ask the partner because the governor the
Ministry of Education person likely
knows that information. I am glad to go
ask that person for you but now I'm
partnering on someone else's partner.
>> Yeah.
>> Bad move.
>> The [snorts] other thing is is that's
not the question to ask. The question to
ask is how many kids are going to school
when we're not there?
How [clears throat] are the parents
feel? What curriculum is being taught?
Do they have a PTA? Do they need a PT?
You know, where are we in the process?
We can't keep going. How many schools
are in this area? But all that work and
then 2007 comes in and again we're just
making years up in this case and it's
like talk about farming.
>> Yeah.
>> We did the same thing in Afghanistan.
>> Yes.
>> Where you know it it's all about it's
all about uh building a new electrical
grid.
>> Yeah. until it's not and it was never
finished and then it's all about, you
know, farming and then it's not. Then
it's all about heroin poppy and then
it's not and and so nothing gets done
and in the end after 20some years they
just throw us out.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Why does anybody partner
with us?
>> I don't know. I told the story the other
day that I I've been to Yemen five times
over the years starting in 1990 through
2011. Every time I go, it's worse than
the previous time. But I went in like
2000.
I'm going to say it was like [snorts]
maybe it was 2000. And I went to see I
paid a call on the
on the Dutch ambassador and the Italian
defense attaches and they were so proud
because their governments had just built
a new sewer system and water treatment
facility for the capital SA
and it took you know 15 years
>> right
>> why couldn't we do that
>> you know and I've always maintained, you
and I had this conversation last time we
spoke, but I've always maintained that
if you want to really fight terrorism,
you do it through economic development.
>> Sure.
>> You you you develop these economies to
the point where these guys have jobs and
they don't need to make jihad against
the Americans. They're not interested in
making jihad against the Americans. Um,
and for whatever reason, the European
Union countries have that long-term
view, and we don't. We don't. I last
time I went to Yemen in 2011, I met with
the US defense attaches and I said, "So,
what are you working on?" And he said,
"Oh, we have this great idea." He says,
"We developed
a a propaganda program modeled on NPR."
>> Jesus Christ.
>> That's going to play jazz on the radio
and it's going to be call-in shows for
young Yemen.
And I was like, "What kind of stupid
idea was that? Whose whose stupid idea
was that?"
>> Yeah.
>> And of course, it lasted, you know, two
weeks and then it shuttered because
nobody's going to listen to that
silliness. What a waste of money and
time.
>> Yeah.
>> And you take all those initiatives and
you put them, bolt them to the ground
and have Pete run around and check
what's going on. Are these things
working? And this this for a lot of
people doesn't sound like spying, but
this is all about what we do. We
>> Oh, yeah. Everything.
>> Absolutely.
So, we pro I probably have told you this
story, but the um it's a brigade I'm
working with and every day the
electronic warfare officer comes out and
he's like, "Oh, you to my slide to the
north. We have radio broadcasting re
they call it re rehab. Everybody radio
in a box." He's drop it in, plug it on,
turn the radio on. Everybody loves it.
And whenever I do my Texas accent, you
know, I'm mocking things. So, um big
circle on the map broadcasting all this
overlap. And so, I'm like, "All right."
So, I take one of our crank radios and I
go out and I listen. Nothing. Nothing.
Nothing. And I compel my little remote
local commander and I'll say, [snorts]
"I'm told that there's going to be a
rehab in that building over there. Can
we go over there real quick?" And the
commanders are always great. Yeah, Pete.
Of course, because they they've learned
that like I'm going to give them things
that nobody else gives them. So, we take
a fiveminute detour and no radio in that
building. [snorts] So, then this is all
the whole machine is broken. So from the
very top, the bad idea of jazz and
everything else and what I'm told people
love. And so [laughter]
go in and I talk to the electronic
warfare officer and I'm like, "Hey,
listen. I got some bad news coming.
There are no radios where you say they
are." And not only not broadcasting, but
physically not present. They're like,
"But that's title nine or whatever
money." And they lose their minds,
right? Um, but that guy does not care
that those things are not there. So I'm
trying to pre-brief him on what I'm
going to brief. But I've purposely held
my report so that he didn't get
torpedoed.
>> Yeah.
>> And he basically gives me a middle
finger because he doesn't care who I am.
Has no idea. And so and I'm like,
"Listen, I I'm begging you." And so I
did I didn't I asked three times. That's
what I do. All right. Here's what's
going to understand. I'm going to brief
this in half an hour. And [snorts] so I
said across guy doesn't even care. So I
brief, hey, uh keep So he briefs his
part. I raise my hand. Uh sir, that I've
been on the ground out there. None of
those radios exist. None of them are
squawking. There's nothing there. They
haven't been there. No one knows the
last time they were there. And by the
way, there's this has happened more than
once in these locations.
And so the commander turns bright red,
steam coming out of his ears. He calms
down, looks at that guy, and that guy
looks at me. And then that guy comes
back up to me in the cow hall later on.
He's like, "Why'd you do that to me?"
What?
So we have these beliefs. This is the
the strategy having no linking to the
ground. And it's all messed up. we're
going to do radio literacy for women,
you know, and all right, let me go look.
Let me go look. And it we still brief
that at at Naval Postgrad. We still
brief the success of that program.
>> Oh my god.
I went to uh I went down to Key West
when I was the senior investigator on
the Senate Foreign Relations uh
committee to do a study on the
effectiveness or lack thereof of radio
and TV. Marti, which of course is the
propaganda radio and television station
that we beam at um at Cuba,
>> right?
>> Um
I've long been opposed to radio and TV
Martin. It's a waste of the taxpayers
money. And besides, the uh the Cubans
jam it anyway,
except when there's a baseball game on,
they let that in. And so, um, I went
down to Key West. We went up in the
plane. They they broadcast the radio
station from a plane. It just flies up
and down the coast of Cuba, up and down
and up and down all night long.
And um, it was kind of cool. You could
see the lights of Havana
and then we would broadcast and and they
would jam. They have these jammers on
the tops of some of the taller buildings
in in central Havana. Then I went to
Cuba two years ago and a buddy of mine
said, "Hey, you know, I've I've always
wondered,
we know that they that they jam Radio
Marti and TV Marty. They they can't get
TV Marti except in the waiting room at
the American Embassy when people are
waiting for their visas. We we play TV
Marty." So, um, he said, "Do me a favor
and just see if you can pick up radio
stations from Miami. I'm curious."
>> Yeah.
>> My god. Miami radio stations. Atlanta,
Dallas, Chicago.
You could get 50 radio stations from the
United States every night. You don't
need to propagandize the Cuban people.
They're already propagandized just by
listening to regular American radio
stations. So we didn't need to spend
millions and millions of dollars
broadcasting radio and TV Marti from a
freaking cargo plane
>> going up and down the coast all night
long every night.
>> Ridiculous.
>> This and this is the playbook, right?
And so when Pete gets to a place, I'm
going to immediately look into SCOPS
because I know they're broken, you know,
and I'm not talking bad about anybody
individually, but they're just it
doesn't work. And so
>> I target these things, you know, like um
for the wa anybody watching, like what
you would hand me is a list of
questions. They call them information
requirements. There's different levels
of how important they are. And I'm like,
what a bunch of adorable little babies
with their little questions. Where are
the bombs? Oh, let me go around town and
ask that question. How about I tell you
where you're losing and getting your ass
kicked and do you want? And every
commander wants to know that. And so
there's the radio is this is just one
area of failure that I could reliably
find every mist because we were the same
people. It wasn't about them. So I would
be told all the time, oh the Afghans
love this. Okay. Well, let me go do
Scop's job and ask. And I'm using this
one particularly for you because I know
you're going to appreciate this.
[snorts] And so I go talk to the farmers
and I'll just say the farmers, it's the
people, whatever it is. I'm like, "What
do you think about that radio?" And then
they'll say things like, "Yeah, I don't
understand what you guys are doing. What
are you talking about?" Because um your
Quranic messages,
those are city folks. I don't even
understand what they're talking about. I
don't understand the words. I don't
understand the message. It's not even
accurate. So, of course, I take this
back to the boss like, "Hey, uh that
doesn't work." I was like, "Oh, yeah.
Well, they don't understand the Quran."
Like, okay, [laughter]
that's the message.
>> Yeah. But you do.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And it wasn't the commander
that says this, but this is the message
that comes back. And so, by the way,
it's all recorded at like, you know, the
So, everybody uh Afghanistan is divided
into commands. And so, the main command
here in the making, it's like gathering
a bunch of states together. So, imagine
like the western state command or the
southwestern state command. And that's
where [snorts] these messages generate
from is these large areas. And again,
it's city folks with city folk accent.
So, they got actual Afghans recording
these messages, but they're not holy
men. they're uh they have, you know, a
Kandahar accent and so it's supposed to
be uniting people and I can't prove that
it's doing the opposite
more than would even be possible.
>> Well, it it it's very much it's very
much like our efforts to combat u
corruption in Afghanistan. Afghanistan
is very very heavily tribal. And so what
what we decided to do, some genius in in
the Pentagon decided to um make the
regional chiefs of police
come from other tribes in other parts of
the country. So if you were from Harat,
you're going to head uh the police force
in Kandahar. If you're in from Kandahar,
you're going to head the police force up
along the border with Tajikistan. And
all that did was made people hate
representatives of other tribes even
more than they had previously.
>> Yeah.
>> And it did nothing to combat corruption.
Nothing.
>> So this and I I'm illustrating this with
you because you know you're working at
CIA or national levels and I'm working
at the personto person level and we just
see the same kind of chaos.
We don't have a license. We don't have a
licensing mechanism. And by the way, you
and I aren't ever going to talk.
>> Yeah.
>> So you and I are never gonna We don't
even organizationally aligned to it. If
I showed up, I would have to use all of
my ability that I would use in town. I
would have to use it on you. And maybe
maybe you the you that would be sitting
there. Maybe you'd want to hear from me,
but probably tune me out. I got to go to
salsa night. No offense. I got to go to
salsa night. I got other things. And and
so this guy that has information you
can't get anywhere else that's always
filtered by the time it gets to you is
completely irrelevant. And I have no
idea how to help you drive me to the
right place because you would be able to
put me right here's what I need. I don't
know where this is, but Pete, here's
what I need right here. [snorts]
>> We don't have that machine either. And
and so as great as we are at Intel,
we're very passive about it. We don't
like to go on offense.
>> No, that's right. And I think frankly
we're not terribly good at Intel.
I I I
>> Yeah. No, I mean
>> we we've we've got nothing to show for
for 20 years of work.
>> Yeah.
>> Literally nothing to show but a bunch of
dead bodies.
>> I mean, they they they
chose the Taliban
over a western style democracy because
they had no no history of Western style
democracy. They had a system that that
they used for 2,000 years and they stuck
with that system and they just realized
that that the stuff we were offering was
not interesting to them.
>> Yeah.
>> And you know, I say all the time too,
Pete, that the Taliban didn't come down
from the moon, you know, and just land.
These are the the fathers, the brothers,
the sons
>> Yeah.
>> of Afghan women. This is what they
chose.
>> Yeah.
Yeah. through political power, physical
power, all the all the different things.
The uh Yeah. And and I'm just going to
beat on the counter intelligence people.
I I came across the team, army counter
intelligence team. I'm working in a
contract ro I'm supporting. And they
wanted me to interview all the Afghans
on the camp. There weren't that many
because it was really remote, really
shitty out there, dangerous as hell. And
then they wanted me to do one-time
sources. And so I go to the contract
company. I'm like, "Oh, hold on. What do
you all think is a onetime source?"
Yeah. Because we're we're in a legal
zone. and nobody could tell me. So, I'm
like, "No, we're not I'm not doing that
at all because no one no one is going to
have my back if anything happens because
they don't even know what a onetime
source is. So, [clears throat]
[laughter] I'm effectively wasting
everybody's time and money, but as long
as someone's sitting in that chair,
everybody's happy." So, I was I didn't
have the right machine to legally screen
or vet people. And so, my job was to sit
there and essentially do nothing all
day. Well, I'm not going to do that. I'm
entrepreneurial. I'm a spy. I'm going to
find work. So, I start finding work. and
I and the counter intelligence team
shows up as they bounce around [snorts]
and what are they doing their screening
and I'm like well that could be me doing
that for you so you guys can go on
offense and go see what you can do and
then no um we just you're doing all
these linguists and everything and we
recommend them all for termination
because they're all tied to the Taliban
we're in coner right and I'm like I'm
like and as a warrant officer everybody
warn officers are are technicians these
are experts right in their field at
least in in position and I'm looking at
him like chief what's going on here. I
want every bad guy you can get. Bring
all of them. Let's go. Let's bring him
onto this camp and let's have him work.
And then, you know, they're saying
things like, "Well, they're going to
find out where the fuel farm is." Like
the fuel farm. Like, we're on the side
of a mountain, man. This mountain up
10,000 ft above us. You are worried
about where the They know where the fuel
farm is. Guess what? They can watch
helicopters come in and feel. And it was
like the dumbest thing, John.
The people who were supposed to protect
the force, the counter intelligence
people were afraid to go on offense. And
when I brought this up, they kicked me
off the camp,
>> you know, because I was the problem.
Like, I'm trying to work here. And I had
I didn't have to work with them. And I
was glad to ignore them because I I had
they had some special operations guys
like we'd love to have you. And I'm
like, let me get myself sorted out. But
[snorts] uh no, rather than fix that
problem, rather than deal with it, and
think about this, all these linguists
are going to work no matter what. So
when people talk about vetting, we're in
the world of vetting now. And [snorts]
it it doesn't mean anything. I'm not
magic. You're not magic. We could talk
to people, make a guess, but I'm telling
you right now, if a person's close to
being, you know, if they're not just
seething with rage after they've been
coached and talked to me,
>> um I'm going to bring them on the camp
because I'm going to put money in their
pockets because I'm hoping like if in
the beginning that they'll be like,
"Hey, Americans aren't so bad." Right.
Yeah.
>> And if they are bad, let me find them.
Let me talk to them. Let me do my job
and flip that person.
>> Yep. Yeah, you're exactly right.
>> How many double oper double agent
operations do you think we've had that
were successful in Iraq or Afghanistan
if you were to guess? And it's
impossible number to guess, but what
would you say?
>> D successful doubles.
>> Yeah.
>> Zero or close to zero,
>> right?
>> I'm serious. Listen, I was at the CIA
for 15 years. I handled I handled one
double agent. Um I mean by their very
nature the double double agent
operations usually don't work
>> right. Yeah.
>> And we're besides the fact that we're
just not good at it.
>> We're not good at it.
>> No.
>> We're terrified of it.
>> Yeah.
>> I'm going to bring a dangerous man on
this camp and I'm going to partner with
that person and uh and they're going to
work for us.
>> Yeah. Well, you you see what happened at
host. You know y deadliest day in the
CIA's history.
Yeah. So there's [laughter] this back to
the overall. Is there any fix in this?
Is there any should we be involved in
it? Can we create a licensing program?
So it's like, hey, this is how we
actually do this. Like I can ask you,
you went to Yemen. I know you speak
Arabic. How hard is it to understand
that? Because they probably don't speak
the Queen's Arabic there. They probably
speak.
>> Oh, they do.
>> That's the That's the only place where
they speak pure Arabic.
>> Really?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. In fact, when I was studying
Arabic, it's called fussa. Uh it's high
standard Arabic,
>> right?
>> The only place where that is spoken is
Yemen. And when I was in Saudi Arabia,
people asked me why I spoke Arabic like
Shakespeare.
>> Yeah.
>> And I said because I was studying fuss
and they were like, "Ah,
okay." And then for my second year, it
was uh khali, the golf dialect,
>> right? Yeah. Which again, like we teach
everybody modern standard that's great,
but then you get to Iraq and they have
totally different words for
Yeah. Right. I mean, yeah. Right.
Actually, I would use we would use um
northern Iraqi words as bonafites
>> because they could say things like it
was watermelon then they would say dipsy
instead of ruggi. I don't know e which
whatever it was. It was a word that
nobody understood unless you were from
Mosul. And uh it was great. is a great
way to do bonafites because it would not
sound like we were saying anything funny
thing about bonafites everybody is like
it's never like the hawk flies on Monday
it's never that because that makes no
[__] sense
>> no
>> it's [snorts] something like hey John
how are you and then that's the bon it's
the beginning of the thing so um yeah
even the Arabic part right or the
language part is we struggle with
>> still after after all these years of war
and occupation and we still struggle
with the language
[snorts]
>> is it possible to operate inside of Do
you think?
>> Um, yeah, it's it's possible, but it's
exceedingly difficult.
>> Yeah, exceedingly difficult. You know,
we were we were trained to do two or
threehour SDRs, surveillance detection
routes.
>> Um, and in China, you're talking about
an eight hour surveillance detection
route. Even even then, the Chinese may
have had a drone on top of you the whole
time you were doing it or they're using
infrared technology or heat sensing
technology or, you know, it's it's very
very difficult.
>> Yeah. I don't even know that SDRs are
even relevant anymore.
>> I Yeah, I know. I know, right?
>> Yeah. We teach them. You got to. I guess
>> you got to. And then what you do is you
have to you have to mix them up. So
instead of just getting in your car and
driving around because your car has
probably got a beacon stuck on it
somewhere or they've hacked into the
car's computer system, you got to do it
on foot. You got to do it on on um uh
public transportation. You've got to
switch cars out, you know, drive into a
parking garage and switch to a rental
car that somebody else rented in a
different name. And it's very difficult.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I was talking with Jack
Barski. Everybody doesn't know Jack
Barski was an agent who was inserted in
America working against us and they made
the show The Americans based upon his
life. And I because you know because I
know our world. I'm like so at what
point did it just become impossible to
do all the the counter this and the
counter that so you weren't discovered?
He's like it became just like I could
never sleep, you know, because you're
always worried about getting caught. The
longer you're there, the more you think
your heat stakes have risen. And so he's
like, yeah, it became Yeah. And Jack
ended up flipping and going to the FBI
because
he he knew that he wasn't supposed to be
here permanently,
but his girlfriend had had their
daughter
>> and he said looking at that child,
he knew I can never go back. And so they
summoned him and he just ignored it. and
he got onto the subway in Queens to go
into Manhattan one day and he's just
standing there holding the the strap and
um and there's a guy next to him and the
guy whispers to him and says, "You know,
if you don't go back, they'll kill you,
right?"
And so he decided that day I'm calling
the FBI.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Didn't he also say that he
had AIDS? I guess
>> that's how he got out of it. Yeah. He
said he couldn't go back because he had
AIDS and he was dying. Yeah.
>> Which of course he just made up off the
top of his head. [laughter]
>> I mean that's that's
>> Jack Jack's a fascinating guy.
Absolutely fascinating guy.
>> Yeah.
>> Do we do we have the stomach to run that
kind of an op an insertion op that the
lifetime? Right. I don't think so.
>> No. No.
>> Very few countries do. This isn't a this
isn't a diss against the United States
or or the American intelligence
community. But the Russians have a very
very long view for what they call their
illegals program. There was a an
illegals network that was broken up
right here in my neighborhood two or
three years ago. I live in Arlington,
Virginia. And right here in my
neighborhood, there was a woman who was
an elementary school teacher that was
actually a Russian sleeper and she was
here 20 years just waiting to be
activated.
>> Yeah.
>> It's incredible. We would never do that.
We don't have the patience for something
like that. Well, also if we gave you
that assignment, you would know to not
trust anybody when you came back because
no one would know who you were. They
would have no idea what you were doing.
They wouldn't believe you if you told
them. And the one thing I learned from
Lawrence of Arabia was that when you
show up in flowing shaky robes at the
the British command, they have no idea
who you are. You have zero influence.
And so that's what taught me like I'm
always balancing the equation on our
side. I'm always seeking relevance on
our side because if I don't then then I
may as well go home
>> if I'm not impacting day-to-day
operations because it's great to go off
and do that adventure. And it was great.
Wonderful things, right? But not
relevant not relevant at all to anything
going on dayto-day. And so the people
who don't know what to worry about are
not worried about you and you're not
contributing to the fight.
>> That's right. That's the bottom line
right there.
>> Yeah. Can we improve that? Can we make
that better? I like the army counter
intelligence is picking up more of the
LEO mission that it had originally and
we certainly need a lot of counter
intelligence in this nation. Army
wouldn't be the the tool inside the
nation but we have so many threats that
we open I mean just in China we have
open more cases than we can sustain and
that's the ones we find.
>> Yeah. There was a revelation in the New
York Times about six months ago about
these um Chinese nationals who have um
what appear to be ties to uh the Chinese
police and they're just operating out of
storefronts around Manhattan
driving or flying around America to
threaten Chinese people. Like stop
talking about China or we're going to
arrest your aunt and uncle in Beijing
and we're going to beat the [__] out of
them. That kind of thing.
>> Yeah.
>> So, I don't know how the FBI missed it.
>> Yeah. Uh but yeah, that's kind of one
example of what we need to shut down.
>> Well, we we all miss it. I mean, we the
Epoch Times focuses on this. They've
been posting this forever. The guy who
runs that Chinese New York beat has been
saying it's all going on. And I I
interviewed him uh in a bar in New York
City right at the very beginning of of
uh co, you know, like the last time you
really could get together in New York
City as a big group. and he was talking
about all this stuff and it was it was
incredible like if half of what he said
was true it was a significant problem
and you and I both know China has a
gigantic almost an unlimited
intel asset you know anybody can be
turned into somebody for the state and
you it's very hard to com combat that.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It's true.
[clears throat]
What when you think about building folks
like us, NOCA is good at it, but are if
you're going to be critical of your
peers, are we good at it? Are we good at
reliably getting people? And then are
are we good at getting the most out of
them? How do we how do we know when you
have someone who's great?
>> I don't think we're good at it.
>> Okay. if if we were there would never
have been a 911,
you know, um or
the bottom line is we've we've missed
every major world event. We've gotten
wrong just about every major world event
from 1947
to to the Russian invasion of Ukraine.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I I don't think we're good at it.
Part of the part of the problem is
we just have never taken foreign
languages seriously. Hard foreign
languages. I'm not talking about
learning Spanish in high school,
>> right?
>> I mean, you know, speaking
>> Farsy, Arabic, Dari, Pashtu, Udu, Cindi,
Punjabi, Tajik, all these, you know,
Mandarin, Russian, Korean, all these
hard languages. We just don't we don't
do it.
>> Yeah. And if you're going to build that
person in this just for the case of
geoloccation so everybody understand if
you were going to have someone operate
in Switzerland you would want them to
speak French German Italian and English
because that's what everybody there does
and to not do that would would make you
lower than the level of the game would
>> as well as the language of your target
if it's yeah right right [snorts] so
even if we chose to build that capacity
you know, at least with the army side,
it you have to be willing. You're not a
maverick, but you look like a maverick
to everybody in the institution. You
know, I'm not going to wear gear. I'm
going to go do this. Yes, I'm going to
drink. Yes, I'm going to mistake do make
mistakes about because if I'm not making
mistakes, I'm making the first mistakes.
So, what we do is dangerous to the
institution. It causes them heartburn
all the time. And it's easier to turn
this off, push Pete over there, keep him
in the office than it is to push Pete
forward.
>> Yeah.
>> He might find out or you might find out
that the Poppy thing isn't what we all
brief, right? It's like, hey,
>> oh, the Poppy thing that was pretty much
our Poppy. I mean, when it came down to
it.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. it, you know, and I I don't want
to get dismayed because I want things to
be positive, but I just don't know that
our foreign policy
it really reliably works.
>> I agree. And it changes so quickly.
You know, there I I complained about
this on a podcast earlier today u that
our our foreign policy changes as
quickly as every four or eight years.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And there there's an old
saying we don't have there's no such
thing as permanent friends it's
permanent interests but even our
interests change
you know when [snorts] we complain about
countries openly complain about
countries that have been our friends for
se two centuries
>> and we disrespect them publicly
>> why would they do what we want them to
do when we turn around you know just
after disrep respecting them and and
order them in public to do something
doesn't make sense.
>> I'm not I'm not a big fan of Hillary
Clinton, but uh No, not but she one time
told the people of Pakistan to overthrow
their leader.
You got you can't you can't do that, you
know, and and that's not this is just an
observation. We're bad on both both
sides of the aisle at this stuff. But
yeah, it it's u it's frustrating. It's
frustrating to see us with all this
influence and I'm always wondering like
how why why do these countries do this?
Why do the Kurds ever trust us? They
they never should.
>> That's a great example.
That's a great example. We have screwed
the Kurds at every turn in history.
>> Right.
>> We have every opportunity. And we
refuse. All these presidents talk all
these big games about all these things.
Just draw a circle and say that's
Kurdistan.
>> Do it. You know, I'm not saying it's a
good good idea or bad idea. I'm just
saying you all talk about this stuff,
but you don't do the very thing that you
could do.
>> Yeah. You know,
>> it's true.
>> There was very briefly from 1946 to 1949
an independent Kurdistan.
>> Right. Right.
>> And and it just went away.
>> The uh the Assyrians, they don't have a
country,
>> you know. The Yazidis don't have any
real protection. And we only care about
them after they've been slaughtered. No
one for about 10 minutes. and cared
about Yazidis as they were being ripped
apart by ISIS and then we stopped
caring. I interviewed a ton of Yazidis.
These are the most peaceful farminist
having a lot of kids in his people and
that's it. That's what they are.
>> They're simple people doing simple
things and they're they're an ancient
people living in a modern world.
>> And then we allowed ISIS to slaughter
the men and to to rape and kidnap and
and sell as sex slaves the women.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Gosh, it's terrible.
To talk about
terrible. Oh my gosh. Yeah. Yeah.
When you think about our profession,
how do we how do we remain principled in
a in an illprincipled world?
>> You know, to me that was an that was the
easy part.
>> Okay. You you go into this life with
your own set of moral values or if you
don't then you're going to fail and
you're part of the problem.
>> Right?
>> I knew right from wrong even if my
superiors were trying to convince me
otherwise.
It was really as simple as that.
>> [snorts]
>> It is a world though where where the the
norms the mores the ethics
uh are situational
>> quite often and it's uncomfortable to
navigate that. Can we develop that
capacity? So like we had a um I worked
at a a source ops course called counter
intelligence force protection source
operation course so for short and we had
this uh Mormon officer and I'm like hey
listen you're going to have to be
willing to do things that are against
your religion to do this job well or or
or stay out of the field because if
someone offers you a shot of Rocky or
whatever it's going to be you have to be
willing to drink that. like I can't like
then you should lead not go out because
someone may die because you don't want
to drink that drink or whatever that
thing is.
>> Yeah. So these there they are
situational things you know like you can
we we terminated a guy in Iraq and uh we
didn't want him to come back so we made
it very clear he was working with us and
when we say terminate everybody we're
not talking about
>> no terminate means to fire him
>> right but we did terminate him in a way
that probably
ended his life, you know, because he was
becoming we weren't sure which side he
was on. He was doing crazy things. And
so when we terminated, we made it
public, you know, and we're like, "All
right, no longer working with us next
time." You know, kiss on each chick. And
so we never saw him again. [snorts] And
in a time when a lot of Rockies got
killed, but I struggled with that ever
since we did it.
>> Yeah.
>> But I didn't know what else we could do.
>> That's not good.
>> Yeah.
>> Wow.
Ah. Um, okay. We got 10 minutes left and
I know you're super busy and you gave me
this extra time in the beginning so I
don't want to take any more from you,
but what do you want to what do you want
to what are you working on now? What do
you want to talk about?
>> Oh, thanks. I'm working on a bunch of
stuff now. I've got three podcasts
[snorts] and I I'm I'm not sure how long
I can keep up this pace, but I do one
every morning with my friend and
colleague Ted Raw uh that's on Rumble
and YouTube called uh Deep Program. We
talk about the day news. Um, it's live
uh from 9 to 10 every morning. And then
I do one twice a week that's a much
deeper look at the news called uh Deep
Focus uh on YouTube. That one's taken
off. We're we're coming up now on on a
100,000 subscribers and we just started
it in March. Um
>> yeah, it's it's kind of crazy. I I I'm
not sure how it took off like it did,
but um
but uh actually I'm trying to look it up
right now to see how many Yeah, here it
is. to see how many uh subscribers I
have. I'm I'm really blessed by 92,500
subscribers, which is just nuts to me. I
can't believe it. And then I started one
um just two months ago
on Apple Podcasts. It it just now
started up as well on Spotify called um
John Kuryaku's Dead Drop. What Makes a
Spy tick? And we're in the top 2%
of all podcasts worldwide. It's just
nuts.
>> Yeah. Crazy. Um, I've got my my next
book is coming out March 24th, Simon and
Schustster, called Remains of the Day, a
definitive guide to Washington DC's
Historic Cemeteries.
And um, I've I just sent my ninth book
to the publisher
uh, called uh, Whispers in the Dirt, a
definitive guide to the Mafia Graves of
New York City.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah. I've got I'm going to do another
three after that one. And um
yeah, I mean I'm going to start a
speaking tour in February, nationwide
speaking tour. I did it in the UK at in
the beginning of the year, January and
February all around uh um England,
Wales, Scotland, Ireland, Northern
Ireland.
So I'm busier than than I can maintain.
>> Yeah.
>> But but it's a good busy.
>> Well, yeah. and and we were talking
offline, you know, just the ability to
maintain your podcasts that are all
doing well is is tough. Yeah,
>> I put links up for as many as I could
catch in the time that we had it, but
there's the there's the dead drop one.
>> Thank you. That's the one I'm I'm really
the most surprised by. It's just really
really taken off.
>> What do you attribute like do you is
there a moment where like this thing I
mean I've been doing this for a long
time and my show's grown. Wax is winged.
It does everything. But that kind of
multi-show jump is you've done something
right.
>> I a year ago a year ago and I don't know
why, but a year ago I seem to have hit
the YouTube algorithm just right. Right.
>> So I I went from like literally
overnight I went from my my videos
getting 500
views or a thousand views
>> Yeah.
>> to There were two shorts I did one week.
One got 30 million and the other got 38
million.
>> Wow.
>> And I I don't know how or why. It just
happened.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And [snorts] you and I both
know like you've got great stories,
great experiences.
>> Thank you.
>> Yeah, of course. But it isn't that.
There's something else. It's not hard
work. It's not quality of the of the
story. There's something in between that
you you hit.
There's one thing that I that I hope
played a role, Pete. And I I'll tell you
the one thing I'm the most proud of is
it's cost me a lot, but I always tell
the truth.
>> Same.
>> And I think people have come to respect
it.
>> Yeah. [snorts] Yeah. It's it's
unfortunately it's rare, you know, and I
don't have a political motive,
>> you know, so it just I'll tell and and
like all this stuff with Venezuela, you
know, I can only tell you what I know
from being on the ground and combat
operations going on until the boss says
all clear, it is a combat operation to
include shooting people that on the
ground that are possibly still alive.
That we'll say the whistle blows. You
now go on one knee and you start
rendering aid to a person you know you
just killed. You know, that is that is
the nature of combat. You know, if you
don't like that, well, then let's not
send people into harm's way. I'm all
about that. But, uh, that's what combat
is, and there's no getting around it.
>> Yeah, it's true. And when we convince
ourselves that we're the good guys,
we we make ourselves able to commit
terrible crimes, and there's never any
any fallout from it.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Well, I used to ask about
Yemen and the conflict because that's
something they've had conflict there for
quite some time, everybody. And nobody
cared about Yemen until it affected
possibly the cost of chips coming
through the Suez Canal, you know, and
it's like, oh, we need to feed these
people missiles. There's a lot of us
very comfortable with that,
>> you know, and Yemen is
>> got no influence on us.
>> Zero,
>> right?
>> Zero.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Well, I'm
excited for your success.
>> Thank you. It's super awesome. You
deserve it. And
>> you know, as as one person who's been
kicked aside by the machine to another,
man, I I dig what you're doing. I dig
your honesty. And yeah, [snorts] if if I
can ever do anything to help you, please
let me know. I'm all about it.
>> Well, I appreciate that very much. Thank
you. It's a pleasure to see you again.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Everybody, uh, I'll have
another show later on today, so you guys
will get a chance to see more of me. And
John, you can check. Look, it's not hard
to find John. You just type in John
Kuryaki. [laughter]
Figure it out. But most importantly,
support his shows. Whether you're on
Rumble or YouTube, support that stuff
because it's quality. And and John, I
hope you're able to at least keep one or
two of those shows going. I know you got
big things. I have big things.
>> I [snorts] sure hope so. I'm I'm gonna
try hard.
>> All right, cool. All right, let me wrap
this up. I'll see you later.